本期视频由CuriosityStream赞助
This video is supported by CuriosityStream.
在过去十年间 全球的航天工业竞争越来越激烈
Over the last decade, the world of spaceflight has become an increasingly competitive industry.
我们见到了各种财大气粗又有航天梦的私人公司横空出世
We've seen private companies burst onto the scene with money and ambition.
而这些场面已经逐渐成为航天工业的家常便饭
And we're now at the point where scenes like this have become routine.
有了这些黑科技般的火箭回收技术
Through these incredible advancements in rocket reusability,
把东西发射到太空的成本终于有所降低
we've seen the overall cost of getting into space drastically reduce.
当火箭可以复用时 火箭实际的发射成本就变得更加重要了
Once a rocket becomes reusable, the cost of actually launching the rocket becomes far more important
而其中一个重要成本就是发射火箭所需的燃料
and one of the largest costs involved in launching a rocket is the fuel.
本期视频我们将了解把火箭燃料送到太空叉的火箭中背后需要的统筹安排
In this video we're going to look at the incredible logistics
of getting rocket fuel all the way from the ground and into a SpaceX rocket.
我们还将了解太空叉为了降低燃料价格都做了什么
We're also going to look at what SpaceX are doing to reduce the cost of rocket fuel
以及他们未来将如何开始自己生产燃料
and how they plan to start producing their own fuels.
太空叉的猎鹰九号火箭使用液氧和煤油(RP-1)作为燃料
For SpaceX and their Falcon 9 rocket, they use liquid oxygen and a refined kerosene called RP-1.
液氧需要降到很低的温度从而减少体积 让火箭能装的更多
The liquid oxygen needs to be cooled to cryogenic temperatures in order to compress
and fit more into the rocket.
虽然液氧占燃料总量超过三分之二的部分
Although the liquid oxygen makes up more than two thirds of the overall fuel load,
但目前它是两种燃料里最便宜的 每公斤只要20美分
it's by far the cheapest of the two fuels, coming in at just 20 cents per kilogram.
而煤油相比来讲则贵了不少
RP1 on the other hand is a little bit less affordable.
太空叉刚开始用猎鹰九号的那阵
When SpaceX were first starting out with the Falcon 9,
他们每公斤煤油要付两美元
they were paying around $2 for every kilogram of RP1.
一番谈判过后 价格有所降低 已经和航空煤油差不多了
After renegotiating, they were able to lower the cost until it was closer to the price of jet fuel,
大约每公斤70美分
at around 70 cents per kilogram.
最后算下来 整枚猎鹰九号火箭燃料价格在15万美元左右
Overall, the cost to fill an entire Falcon 9 sets SpaceX back around $150,000.
但实际上 猎鹰九号不可能做到完全可复用
But realistically, the Falcon 9 will never be fully reusable
毕竟每次发射都需要一个崭新的二级火箭
since a brand new second stage has to be built for each flight.
因此 燃料费用仍然是整个发射费用的很小一部分
Because of this, the fuel costs will remain a small fraction of the overall launch cost.
但对于太空叉的Starship 燃料就重要得多了
But for SpaceX's Starship rocket, the fuel will be far more important.
在短短几年里
In just a couple of years,
太空叉就将德州一块烂泥地变成了他们Starship的高级试验场
SpaceX turned a dirt field in Texas into an advanced testing site for their Starship rocket.
每一次试验 太空叉都要消耗大量燃料
With each and every test, SpaceX goes through an enormous amount of fuel.
那么Starship使用什么燃料？太空叉又如何弄到这些燃料的？
But what fuel does Starship use and how do SpaceX get it?
要想回答这个问题 我们要先了解一下太空叉的任务总体内容
In order to answer this we need to look at SpaceX's overall mission.
他们想用Starship送人类移民火星
With their Starship rocket, they want to take humans to Mars in a sustainable way
让人类在火星上可以建造基地并进行殖民
where they can set up bases and begin colonizing the planet.
往返火星需要大量的能量
It takes an enormous amount of energy to get to and from Mars
但如果我们能在火星表面制造燃料 就能极大减少任务总体花销
but if we could produce fuel while we were there, it would cut the overall cost massively.
所以Starship将使用甲烷和液氧作为燃料
That is why Starship will use methane and liquid oxygen as it's propellants.
两种燃料都能在火星表面找到
Both of these propellants can be found on Mars
甲烷可以从火星大气中获得 氧气可以从地下冰层中获得
through the methane in the Martian atmosphere and the oxygen in the subsurface ice.
而甲烷在地球上也是最便宜的化石燃料
Methane is also a perfect choice since it's the cheapest form of fossil fuel found on Earth.
那么太空叉如何将甲烷运输到他们的发射场呢？
So how do SpaceX get liquid methane to their launch site?
液化天然气(LNG)的主要成分就是甲烷
Liquefied natural gas which is mostly made up of methane
通常可以在地表下的天然气田中找到
can be found in reservoirs beneath the Earth's surface.
钻探公司会使用陆上或海上的钻井平台从天然气田中开采天然气
Mining companies use off-shore and onshore platforms to access and extract the gas from these reservoirs.
此时的天然气还包含氮气、水和二氧化碳
At this point, the LNG still contains nitrogen, water and carbon dioxide,
因此它将经由管道送往处理设施中分离这些组分
so it's piped to a treatment facility where these components are split up.
当甲烷与其他成分分离后
Once the methane is separated from the other elements,
它会被泵入液化设施进行冷却
it gets piped to a liquefaction facility to be cooled.
此时的甲烷仍然是气态的 在冷却到-162摄氏度后会转为液态
The methane which is still a gas at this point, gets cooled to -162 degrees where it turns into a liquid.
液化后的甲烷体积会变为原来的六百分之一
Once the methane is in liquid form, it takes up 1/600th of the volume.
这也是为什么火箭上会使用低温燃料
This is why cryogenic propellants are used on rockets,
因为体积小装得多
so they can be compressed to fit as much in as possible.
液化完成后 在转运之前 液态甲烷会一直储存在隔热罐中
After the liquefaction process, the liquid methane is stored in insulated tanks until it's ready to be shipped.
最近的LNG工厂在德州的布朗斯维尔 离发射场只有30公里
The nearest LNG facility for SpaceX is in Brownsville Texas, just 30km away (from their launch site).
太空叉会委托运输公司GENOX来运输绝大多数的液态甲烷
From there, SpaceX uses the transportation company GenOx to transport most of their liquid methane.
他们使用特别定制的最先进的拖车来储存液态甲烷
They use state of the art trailers specifically designed to hold liquid methane.
在去博卡奇卡的路上
For the trips to Boca Chica,
13000加仑≈49.2立方米
每辆拖车可以运送13000加仑的70psi的液态甲烷
each trailer can transport up to 13,000 gallons of liquid methane at a pressure of 70psi.
虽然这个压强已经挺高了
Although this is a relatively high pressure,
但此时甲烷的密度其实还没有在Starship中的时候高
the methane is actually less dense at this stage than it will be when it's in the Starship rocket
后者工作时甲烷压强接近100psi
since it's operating pressure is closer to 100psi.
甲烷运输到太空叉发射场后
Once the liquid methane arrives at the SpaceX site,
会被慢慢泵入太空叉储存燃料的巨大罐体中
it's slowly pumped into the massive tank farm where SpaceX stores their propellants.
单为一发Starship加满燃料就需要好几辆拖车
It takes several trailers just to transport enough methane for one Starship
所以每次测试中间经常能看到甲烷罐车来来回回的跑
so methane deliveries are a common sight between each test.
虽然太空叉现在是从外面采购他们多数的燃料
Although SpaceX are currently outsourcing most of their propellants,
但在本场生产燃料也不是什么稀奇事
it's also common for propellants to be sourced on site.
由法国液化空气集团(Air Liquide)运营
在肯尼迪航天中心 NASA就有自家的液氧工厂
At the Kennedy Space Center, NASA has their own liquid oxygen plant (operated by Air Liquide),
每天能生产265吨液氧
which can liquify up to 265 tonnes of oxygen per day.
太空叉打算在博卡奇卡这边也造一个类似的设施
SpaceX are looking to create a similar setup at their Boca Chica site.
根据马一龙所说 太空叉会在设施附近造一个风力发电站
According to Elon Musk, SpaceX will set up a wind farm at their facility
为他们在空气中分离氧提供所需的大量能源
to generate the enormous amounts of energy needed to separate oxygen from the air.
这个过程需要将空气加压到100psi后液化
This process involves compressing air to around 100psi and turning it into a liquid.
之后液态空气会经过一系列的过滤器
This liquid air is then passed through various filters
移除水蒸气和二氧化碳等会冻结堵住设备的物质
to remove things like water vapour and carbon dioxide which could freeze and block the machinery.
为了将空气中的氧气 氮气和氩气分开
In order to separate the air into oxygen, nitrogen and argon,
液态空气会按顺序提升到各个组分的沸点
the liquid air is systematically brought up to the boiling point of each element.
因为氮气有三者中最低的沸点 所以会最先变成气体
Since nitrogen has the lowest boiling point of all three, it turns back into a gas first,
从而将它分离出来
which can then be separated from the mix.
然后 氩气会在-186摄氏度沸腾出来 留下的就是纯净的液氧了
Then, the argon boils off at -186 degrees leaving behind pure liquid oxygen.
这个过程需要大量的能源
This entire process requires a huge amount of energy,
但对于这种大量的生产 平均下来经济性就很可观了
but when done at a large enough scale, the economics start to make sense.
因此太空叉可以从法国液化空气集团手里以每公斤20美分的低价购买液氧
This is why SpaceX can purchase their liquid oxygen from Air Liquide for as little as 20 cents per kilogram.
但如果太空叉想要自己造液氧工厂
But with SpaceX planning to build their own oxygen plant,
他们就需要一个巨大的风力发电站来让效益最大化
they will need an enormous wind farm to power it and make it cost efficient.
另外 太空叉可以利用萨巴蒂尔反应从水中分解出氧气
Alternatively, SpaceX could use the Sabatier process of separating oxygen from h2O.
这对于太空叉来说会是一个很好的实践
This would be good practice for SpaceX,
因为他们正打算利用这个反应在火星上制取氧气
since they plan to use this exact method to obtain oxygen on Mars.
最近 人们在太空叉设施一个枯井附近发现他们要有大动作
Recently, people have noticed a lot of activity surrounding an old well on the SpaceX facility.
他们在那架起了一台吊车
A large crane has been set up
多方猜测这可能是他们自建工厂的开端
and people believe this could be the beginning of SpaceX's own propellant facility.
为了尽可能实现碳中和
In order to be more carbon neutral,
太空叉最终选择使用可再生能源自行生产甲烷和氧是合理的
it makes sense that they would eventually start producing their own methane and oxygen
using renewable energy sources.
如果他们能自己生产燃料
And if they can start producing their own fuels,
那么Starship每发价格也可能会有所降低
they might even be able to reduce the cost for each Starship launch.
对于太空叉来说 燃料的生产是一个新的挑战
This world of propellant production is a new challenge for SpaceX,
但长远来看 他们学习的这个新技能点对于他们殖民火星是至关重要的
but it's crucial that they develop the skills and technologies to do this on a large scale
if they want to sustainably go to Mars.
在以前 太空叉可以从外面采购燃料
In the past, SpaceX could rely on outsourcing their fuel
还能使用肯尼迪航天中心的已有设施
and using pre existing infrastructure at the Kennedy Space Center.
但现在他们在博卡奇卡有了自己的发射场
But now that they have their own facility in Boca Chica,
他们就必须从零开始自己建造整套燃料生产系统
they have to design and build all of these fueling systems from scratch.
当太空叉在发射场测试Starship原型机的时候
When testing Starship prototypes at their launch site,
每次都会一直燃着一根甲烷火炬装置
SpaceX used to have a methane flare which would be used during each test.
因为甲烷释放到大气后会引起严重的温室效应
Since releasing methane into the atmosphere on its own contributes massively to global warming,
而火炬装置会把甲烷燃烧后变成二氧化碳再排放到大气中
the flare stack would burn the methane and turn it into CO2 before releasing it into the atmosphere.
虽然这样之后对环境的影响会小很多
Although this is much less harmful to the environment,
但每次测试时自然蒸发的甲烷也是燃料的极大浪费
the constant boil-off of methane during every test was a massive waste of propellant.
为了解决这个问题 太空叉开始将蒸发的甲烷重新收集起来冷凝
In order to get around this, SpaceX started piping the excess methane into a recondenser,
降温后再变回液态甲烷
which cools it down and turns it back into a liquid.
太空叉可以将它们储存起来 供将来的测试使用
SpaceX can then store that methane in their tank farm and use it again for future tests.
虽然他们不会循环利用液氧
Although they don't recycle their liquid oxygen,
但买新的运到发射场会比收集后重新冷凝要更便宜一点
it's cheaper for them to just buy more and ship it to the launch site
than it would be to recondense it after each test.
无论怎样 看到太空叉为了让航天旅行像航空旅行一样便宜
Either way, it's exciting to watch SpaceX revolutionize every little aspect of spaceflight
而在为航天工业中各种细小方面做出改变都是很令人兴奋的
with the aim to make rocket travel just as normal as air travel.
为了能让太空叉能继续实现他们长远目标移民火星
In order for SpaceX to continue with their long term goal of colonizing Mars,
他们需要雇更多的新一代航天爱好者和工程师
they will need to hire the next generation of passionate space and engineering fans.
那么有没有一款……
Feeding the interest of space nerds is crucial in order to make this a reality.
感谢观看本期视频 我们下期视频见！
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.